Yanela Frias doesn't hesitate when
asked what she loves about working at
Prudential.
From a cultural perspective, we're a
purpose driven organization, and that is
really meaningful to me.
It is a group of really smart people
working together, collaborating to meet
the challenges and solve the challenges
of our customers.
And that makes work interesting every
day.
The interesting days have compounded for
27 years into an extraordinary career.
I started in finance.
I spent about 19 years through the
finance organization.
I like to say I grew up in finance.
I spent a number of years in the
corporate Treasury organization where I
probably grew the most there, and then I
went off and was CFO for a couple of
businesses, both the life business and
the annuities business.
And then I said, I want to run a
business.
So that is quite non-traditional.
But I really wanted to experience what
it was like to run a P&L.
But did you always have clarity?
Did you always know,
sort of,
I'm here, but I know where I'm going to next?
Directionally.
To me, it wasn't
I want to be CFO,
I want to be CEO.
To me, it's always been I want to have
growing responsibilities where
I'm challenged every day, where I'm
adding value and where I'm making an impact.
In March 2024, Yanela Frias took on her
most challenging assignment so far as
Prudential's chief financial officer.
CEO Charlie Lowrey says putting her in
that position was an easy call. She
was the right person at the right time.
She understands the business side.
She understands the functional side.
She understands the financial side of
things.
And given that combination of
experiences, we thought she would be a
fantastic CFO and she's turning out to
just knock the cover off the ball.
She's been great.
It's a big job and Frias has embraced
it.
I think one of the biggest surprises and
shouldn't have been a surprise, but
biggest awareness for me was how
vast the role is and how everything that
happens in the organization in one way,
shape or form crosses my desk.
Prudential has become a diversified
global financial services company with a
complex mix of businesses contributing
to its success.
Its future hinges on leaders who can
connect the dots, who can mold a
dynamic array of people, products and
services into a purposeful and
profitable big picture.
Yanela Frias is an accomplished dot
connector.
Need any help on the capital piece or is
that...well the capital piece is interactive.
Having run the retirement business,
having run the group business, having
been many years in our Treasury
organization.
Understanding the opportunities that we
have as an organization and as a
business, but also how do we meet the
needs of customers and do so in a way
that creates value for everyone?
And that's where connecting the dots in
terms of here are the risks we're
taking.
How are we getting paid for those risks?
How are we making sure that we meet our
promises?
We're in the business of making long
term promises, so focusing on financial
strength and being here for another 150
years is top of mind for us.
Prudential's reputation rests on
consistency.
Like the Rock of Gibraltar built into
its logo.
But when Charlie Lowrey became CEO in 2018,
he realized that he had to set the
company on a bold new course.
This company needed to transform,
and there was a lot of hard work that
needed to be done in order to transform
it.
We've been on a journey to be higher
growth, more nimble and more capital
efficient.
There's been a lot of pressure on the
banks since the financial crisis, and so
what you've had is the life insurance
companies filling a lot of that savings
gap.
And in addition, you have the retirement
crisis.
So you have the life insurance companies
also rising to address that
savings for retirement gap.
And then on the asset management side,
you've seen a lot more private credit
because they are working to fill that
gap that has been left in lending.
And so now what you're seeing is that
the two industries are coming together
and it works very well because they both
need AUM. We have the ability to generate
liabilities.
We have an ability to invest that in one
of the world class asset managers we
have.
We have an amazing retirement business.
Our goal is to continue to grow.
We have a lot of opportunities in the
marketplace and we need to do that in a
thoughtful way.
On Lowrey's watch, Prudential streamlined
its processes and reshaped its product
line, putting it on track for record
revenue in 2024.
Lowrey will step down as the CEO in April
2025. While he'll stay for another 18
months as executive chair,
it will fall to the new CEO, Andy
Sullivan and the CFO Frias, to keep the
positive momentum going.
We have lowered our market sensitivity
by reinsuring a lot of different blocks
of business in annuities and life, and
we become more nimble through a lot of
the transformative work we did through
expense savings, through reorganization,
etc.
That work has all been done, but we take
that and we really accelerate into a
growth agenda, which is what Andy and
Yanela and others are going to do.
Prudential is poised to benefit from a
major demographic shift with a record
number of Americans reaching age 65.
More people than ever before are in the
market for retirement, planning, advice
and solutions.
As the company's retirement business
thrives,
Its investment arm, PGIM, has boosted
assets under management by scaling up
its holdings in alternatives.
But even with a mandate to hit the gas,
a CFO must know when to use the brake.
We're an insurance company.
We're in the business of taking risk.
We are looking to diversify our risk
profile because it's important to have
that diversification.
But in order to grow, we have to take
risks.
They have to be prudent.
They have to be thoughtful, and we have
to manage them appropriately.
Are you a CFO
that sort of is in haste to move? Or
again, is it a little bit more cautious,
and I like to have a lot of homework
done before I pull the trigger?
I'm in the middle.
I know that's that's the easy answer,
but no.
So I am incredibly results oriented and
focused on outcomes.
And I like to move quickly, but I like
to move when I have enough information.
But I'm a big believer in, you know, if
you have 100% perfect information, you
studied the problem too long.
Along with risk management,
expense management will be critical to
Prudential's continued success.
I don't get the sense you have to
instill that in Yanela.
I think she struck me as a -- Oh no, you do
not have to instill that in Yanela that
that's part of it.
That's part of the DNA, part of her DNA,
part of why she is so good is she very
much wants to instill that continuous
improvement.
It's about operational efficiency.
It's about doing things smarter with
less.
And I always talk about it as it's a
lifestyle, not a diet.
So let's not go on programs and look to
cut this much and cut that much.
It's about continuous improvement,
operating efficiently and having the
right approach.
And if you do that and you have that
lifestyle, then you're actually
generating funds so you can fund that
growth.
And so it's a flywheel and it's the
approach that we've been taking and it's
allowed us to grow our businesses faster.
To drive productivity and improve
efficiency,
Prudential has made significant
investments in data analytics and
artificial intelligence.
Yanela Frias plays a key role in
integrating these tools into the
company's processes.
We always need people. We're in the people
business. But more and more, if we
really want to provide the right
customer experience, fast access to
products, it's about technology.
Technology has always been an enabler.
Now it's a strategic differentiator.
We expect that by 2027, AI spending will
be about half a trillion dollars between
big tech and corporates.
And so you'll see an arms race to
develop all of these excellent
generative AI solutions that can be used
opportunistically by life insurance
companies who are usually a little bit
more conservative.
But there are many applications for
them, including servicing, claims,
processing and just generally reducing
paperwork and cost.
So we expect that the AI arms race will
be a huge tailwind for the life
insurance company over time.
Give me a sense of AI in particular.
What are you experimenting with?
A few areas.
One is around customer experience.
In our individual life business.
Our underwriting process has gone from
about 20 days to minutes.
In our group business, we have partnered
with a number of different fintechs to
really improve customer experience, to
bring on board capabilities, things like
claims management, where we can process
a disability claim faster and help
people get to work faster.
How much productivity uplift are you
getting and will you get?
We're probably getting 10% at this
point, but I think over time that is
where the value is and it will then
allow us to take our capacity in the
form of people and redirect it to more
value add activities.
In a nutshell, it means turning the
menial into meaningful.
It can be both a huge saver of time, but
it can also provide real insight.
Now where we're going with it.
Let's say you want to see the financial
data every month.
GEN AI will put inferences and say I
see trends over the past three years and
here's what I'm seeing and why.
And it will provide prompts for for our
managers to think about, different issues
that they might not see, sort of
connecting the dots.
For all the intriguing potential of
A.I., Prudential has got a rock solid
asset right at hand.
It's the balance sheet.
Are you 'fortress Balance sheet
first' as a CFO?
Yes, absolutely.
My number one job is capital and
liquidity.
A Double A credit rating and $4 billion
plus in liquidity gives the company
enviable flexibility.
We have a really strong foundation.
At the same time, there are gaps and
capabilities that we need to either
build ourselves or acquire, and we're
doing some of both in our asset
management business.
Yeah, we are looking to enhance
capabilities in private credit in a few
key areas.
And then internationally in emerging
markets, we would be looking for
opportunities to expand as well.
So is that why you'd like to have a
little bit of extra on the balance sheet?
It's always
good to have a little extra.
But then that suggests that you're ready
to act quite nimbly if those
opportunities come.
Yes.
Because you never know when the
opportunities come.
Right.
So having financial flexibility is
about being able to weather difficult
environments and markets can change very
quickly.
But it's also about having the capital
and the currency to act when
opportunities come as well.
Prudential has reliably returned capital
to shareholders through dividends and
share repurchases.
2023 marked the 16th consecutive year of
its increased dividend.
We've kept the level of buybacks
constant for a number of years and we've
raised the dividend slowly over time.
And that's been our philosophy and we've
we've stuck to it.
Is that something that you have believed
is a counterbalance perhaps to the
less aggressive equity performance?
I would have liked, frankly, a better
equity performance than we had.
But we were going through our
transformation.
And as a result, I think investors had a
kind of wait and see attitude about are
you going to deliver on the
transformation and when is that going
to,
when's that going to come into the
numbers?
Which again, I understand. I had
conversations with investors about it.
They say what you're doing is
interesting, but I want to see the
results of that. And the results of that
are going to come in the next few years.
Yanela Frias has spent her entire 27
year professional career at Prudential
and held nearly a dozen jobs at the
company on the way to her current
position as CFO.
She traces her persistence and
resilience to her experience emigrating
from Cuba to the U.S.
with her family at age eight.
When you're that young and you have such
a significant change in your life,
you experience your parents risking so
much for a better life and to provide
their children with a better life.
I think it gave me perspective from a
young age.
It made me very adaptable to change.
It made me really open to taking risks
because risks led to better
opportunities and to good outcomes.
You know, I was the first person in my
family to go to college.
And to this day, every time I get a
promotion, every time something good
happens at work, my dad always says,
that's why I came to this country.
How does that translate to how you
manage as a CFO?
I know you've been in different parts of
the business, but do you think that
experience, that immigrant experience,
defines how you manage the business?
It does.
I mean, I'm definitely thoughtful,
prudent, and I like to understand the
risks, risks I'm taking.
But at the end of the day,
you've got this great perspective and
you do fear less.
And I always think about it as we either are
going to succeed in terms of we made a
decision and it played out well or we
will succeed because I learned
something.
Frias is also a path breaker as the
first female CFO in Prudential's 150
year history.
Sometimes in my position, I don't think
about it too much.
But as I have conversations with women,
actually, even when the announcement
went out, the number of emails and texts
I got from women throughout this
organization not just congratulating me,
but but really acknowledging that this
was a sign that anything was possible
and that they too, could rise through
the ranks.
I think that was really powerful and
obviously personally for me, having two
daughters being the role model for them
and all their friends, it's a great
thing.
As Prudential's head of finance, Yanela
Frias oversees more than 15 billion dollars in
annual retirement income payments to
more than 2 million individual and
institutional customers.
And she empathizes with the struggle for
security in retirement in an era when
pension plans have largely given way to 401Ks.
The challenge is
The 401K was always a tax
advantaged savings vehicle.
It was never meant to replace the
defined benefit plan.
And so what we need to do is help
individuals understand, yes, you need to
save in your 401K plan, but then how do
we turn that into protected income,
Lifetime income?
In this environment, annuities are
gaining traction as a solution, with
sales booming across the entire
industry.
The baby boomers are retiring and
they're really right now, almost today
at that peak age, people at that
retirement age need protection from
downside in the markets.
And so annuities are a great way to get
that.
And longer term, they're going to need
an income replacement.
We have been in the accumulation mode.
Now we're hitting peak 65 in the U.S.,
but think about Japan as well.
We're in the decumulation mode and
people need security of income as they
go forward.
They need lifetime income.
Are annuities back in vogue and here to
stay?
They are.
And I think they're here to stay because
they're a great vehicle to create that
protected income.
And one of the good things is that
annuities have actually gotten simpler
through the cycle, right?
So that we went through the period of
the guaranteed benefits and the living
benefits and annuities became very
complex and expensive, to be fair.
The simplification of
the products, less expensive, I think
that's what what's really brought them
back.
Prudential is a major player in another
robust retirement market:
Pension risk transfer. Deal volume has
soared in this space where employers
sell their in-house pension plans to
insurers, reducing the risk on their
books and helping preserve benefits for
retirees.
You have organizations that are not
insurance companies running an insurance
business on their balance sheet when you
think about the large organizations and
their pension balances.
And so what a pension risk transfer
transaction does is it transfers the
liability and the obligation to an
insurance company that's better equipped
to really manage that and ensure that
those payments are getting to the
annuitants.
We've done seven of the largest ten
deals in the US, and there's a
tremendous opportunity.
There's $3 trillion in pension balances
in the US.
Where do you see the growth in that
pension transfer, that pension risk
transfer?
Are there big opportunities beyond
borders?
Yeah, at some point we think there are
pension risk transfer opportunities
beyond borders.
Today we participate in the UK space
through longevity reinsurance.
We've also participated in Netherlands
again through longevity reinsurance.
We think at some point in Japan that's
an opportunity.
And in Brazil we think over time -- today
we're in life insurance.
But over time the products that will
evolve as well.
How do you drive this business forward?
You've got a great opportunity.
You're sitting into the CFO seat.
You can shape this in your own image.
What's that going to be?
Well, I think a big part of it is how do
we source capital?
The reality is there's not enough
capital in insurance companies today to
meet the need.
When you think about pension risk
transfer, individual annuities.
And so one of the things we're thinking
about is how do we source capital
differently?
So that's where third party capital
comes into play.
So we have a sponsored entity, Prismic
in Bermuda, which is our way of
accessing third party capital to
continue to bring those solutions to the
market.
2025 is a milestone year for Prudential
as the company celebrates its 150th
anniversary.
It's also a year of transition.
Charles Lowrey is set to step down as CEO
at the end of March.
He'll step up to the role of executive
chairman.
I said to the board when I came in, Give
me five years and we'll transform the
company.
And it's been six years.
And I think this is a great time to pass
the baton on to the next leadership.
Prudential's new CEO will be Andrew
Sullivan, who's been with the company
for over a decade.
He and the CFO go way back.
Andy and I have worked together in many
different ways and shapes over the
years.
That's the wonderful thing about being
in an organization so long.
Actually, fun fact: he and I were both
participants at Prudential's inaugural
executive development program ten years
ago.
He's someone I have a lot of respect
for.
He's a great leader.
He's a friend.
And I think I look forward to really
partnering with him.
What do you think he's going to bring to
the role of CEO?
I think Andy brings a new perspective,
energy, a thoughtful approach to how we
really look at our opportunities on a
global basis.
And I think there's incredible
opportunities ahead of us.
How are you going to guide this
transition?
What kind of executive chairman are you
going to be for 18 months?
I will be a very supportive executive
chairman who will be in the background.
I have taken a page out of James
Gorman's book, who was executive
chairman, and he had a series of rules.
He said, don't ever come talk
to me if you haven't talked to the CEO
first.
Andy is the CEO of this company and he
will run it
2025 marks
Yanela Frias's 28th year with Prudential
and the completion of her first year as
CFO.
I asked her what she sees when she looks
into the future.
What is the biggest opportunity for this
organization, Prudential, in the next
decade?
It's really the global retirement
opportunity.
There's just so much in terms of an
aging population, a lack of ability for
the governments to really continue to
support retirement and a need for
individuals to have the ability to save
and then generate protected income.
What is the biggest headwind or
challenge for the organisation in the
next ten years?
Our biggest challenge is prioritizing
our opportunities.
There is a lot that we can do, but we
have limited time, limited resources and
we really need to focus and that's
something that we work really hard on.
How do we prioritize to deliver the best
value to our customers and our
stakeholders?
Complete this sentence.
The hardest part of being a CFO is -- it's
the vast responsibilities, the need
to be engaged in different topics.
You know, in any given day, I can be in
five meetings about five different
businesses.
That takes a lot of energy and a lot of
knowledge, but it's what makes the job
so much fun and so interesting.
What's the one piece of advice you would
give to every young aspiring CFO?
The piece of advice I would give them is
build relationships in your role.
It is a relationship business at the end
of the day.
It's easier to say no to something or to
challenge something when you have a
relationship with an individual and that
goes a long way.
And tell me, if you look backwards and
you have to give yourself a piece of
advice
when you were younger, what would that
be?
I would tell myself not to take myself
so seriously.
I've always been a perfectionist, and
over the years, as I've grown wiser and
older, I've realized, you know,
perspective is important.
Not everything
has to be perfect.
And it's a lot easier to do your job and
do it well when you're more relaxed
about that.
And if a friend called you up and they
said, Listen, great news.
I've just been appointed as CFO --
probably after you say
congratulations, you probably stop and
take a breath.
And then you would say? I would say it's
a wonderful opportunity to really impact
the organization.
You know, I always say to people, I
consider myself the chief instigating
officer because my job is to be
provocative, to challenge the status
quo, to force us to think differently
about our strategy and about our
businesses.
And that's what's so interesting about
this role.
I'm Manus Cranny.
This is Bloomberg.